"Sleep and Anti-Aging Properties
of Melatonin Supplements"
Some experts recommend melatonin
as a first-line agent
to treat insomnia
in older adults.
The World Sleep Society
disagrees
due to its low efficacy.
Subjectively,
people report better sleep,
though objectively,
a meta-analysis of studies
found that melatonin
only helped people
get to sleep 4 minutes faster
and extend
overall sleep duration
by about 13 minutes.
If you do want to try melatonin
to help with sleep,
older adults are advised
to use the smallest
effective dose
an hour before bedtime,
starting perhaps
at 0.3 milligrams.
The 12-milligram supplements
on the market
could produce levels
in the bloodstream
that can be
two hundred times higher
than normal nightly levels,
which raises safety concerns.
After all,
melatonin used to be known
as the anti-gonad hormone,
with human-equivalent doses
of just a milligram or two
reducing the size of sex organs
and impairing fertility
in laboratory animals.
Furthermore,
due to poor regulation
of dietary supplements,
in the U.S.,
you never know
what you're gonna be getting.
An analysis
of thirty-one different brands
of melatonin supplements
found that the actual
melatonin content varied
up to nearly 500 percent
compared to what was listed
on the bottle.
Even within a single brand,
different lots
of the same product
suffered similar variability.
Given that there is
no guarantee
of the strength or purity
of melatonin supplements,
many countries have banned
over-the-counter melatonin,
making it prescription-only
so authenticity
could be ensured.
U.S. citizens can get
certified melatonin
by sending a prescription
to an online Canadian pharmacy
(though it's
technically illegal)
or can get melatonin
from their diet.
Interestingly, the rise
in melatonin blood levels
or metabolites in the urine
consistently exceeds
the amount of melatonin
that's actually ingested
in these foods.
You can even get a spike
in melatonin
after eating fruit
that doesn't even appear
to have any detectable
melatonin at all.
The answer to the puzzle
may lie in the gut.
The first site
outside the pineal gland
where melatonin production
was discovered
was the human appendix.
Although we now know
melatonin can be produced
throughout the body,
the greatest accumulation
appears to be
in the gastrointestinal tract,
estimated to contain more than
400 times more melatonin
than the pineal gland.
So, perhaps the consumption
of certain foods
can cause the release
of some of this bounty
into the bloodstream.
This may be
how magnesium supplements
(500 milligrams a day
for eight weeks)
was able to improve
sleep quality and quantity
over placebo, given the effect
was accompanied by a rise
in melatonin levels.
More intriguing are its
purported anti-aging benefits.
In addition to regulating sleep
and our circadian rhythms
(when properly timed
it can be used
to treat jet lag),
melatonin can have antioxidant
and anti-inflammatory
properties.
However, secretion of melatonin
appears to progressively
decline with age,
dropping as much as 70 percent
between middle and older age.
This has led some to speculate
that "aging is a syndrome of
relative melatonin deficiency
resulting from
the gradual failure
of the pineal gland."
A variety
of age-related diseases
such as Alzheimer's
are associated
with particularly low levels
of melatonin,
but we have yet to determine
if this is a cause
or consequence of disease.
Melatonin supplementation
extends the lifespan
of fruit flies but shortens
the lifespan of C. elegans.
Mice that have had
their pineal glands removed
appeared to age more rapidly,
but when put to the test,
melatonin prolonged survival
of some strains of mice,
but shortened the lives
of others (by inducing cancer).
So, are we more like
New Zealand black mice
or Bagg albino mice?
Sometimes
the same research group
went on to publish
opposite results,
showing melatonin
both increasing
and decreasing lifespan.
Not surprisingly,
a meta-analysis found
no overall effect
when all of the mouse studies
were considered together.
In rats, melatonin
significantly improved survival,
but so did
a melatonin-blocking drug.